Guide to the Jessie Louise Donaldson-Anne Banks Papers 1922-1985
Montana State University-Bozeman Library
Jessie Louise Donaldson-Anne Banks Papers
1922-1985
Montana State University Library, Merrill G. Burlingame Special Collections P.O. Box 173320 Bozeman, MT 59717-3320 United States Phone (406) 994-4242 Fax (406) 994-2851 http://www.lib.montana.edu/archives/ University Archivist spcoll@www.lib.montana.edu
Collection 2186, MtBC, us
5.6 linear feet
The Jessie Louise Donaldson-Anne Banks Papers consist of originals and copies of transcriptions, a set of audio tapes; rough drafts of an autobiography; research notes; drafts of published and unpublished stories; royalty papers; legal agreements; correspondence with publishers, writers, friends and colleagues; color illustrations; pencil drawings; newspaper clippings; photographs; student papers and memorabilia.
Biographical Note
Jessica Louise Donaldson Schultz Graham was born in Minnesota on August 17, 1887. She received her BA from the University of Minnesota in 1913. From 1915-1918, she taught in rural schools in Gallatin County, Montana. From 1918 to 1929, she taught at Montana State College (now Montana State University, Bozeman) in the English Department as an Instructor, Assistant Professor and was Acting Head of the Department during 1923-1924. During her time there, she directed a pageant of the Gallatin Valley in 1919 and in 1927, the production "The Masque of the Absaroka" depicting the Crow Indian cosmogony that involved Native Americans, students and townspeople. Interested in furthering programs for women students, she helped found Cap and Gown (the precursor to Mortar Board), the Women's Athletic Association and most notably the Spurs, for which she wrote the initiation ritual. She resigned from the college in 1929 and earned her MA in Anthropology from the University of California in 1930. In 1931, she married James Willard Schultz, noted for his books about the Blackfeet Indians, with whom she co-authored the book "The Sun God's Children" (a story of the Blackfeet) and started a career as a worker at the Blackfeet Indian Reservation at Browning, Montana. There she became the Community Worker under the WPA from 1937 to 1941. She helped to establish a craft shop at St. Mary, Montana for Blackfeet that featured their native costumes, equipment and tools. These craft industries eventually became a cooperative that substantially raised the income of the Blackfeet. She fostered the careers of individual Indian artists and was instrumental in the establishment of the Plains Indian Museum in Browning. She started a lending library and did social welfare work among the members of the tribe. From 1941 to 1953, she served the same type of position with the Bureau of Indian Affairs at the Wind River Reservation in Wyoming for the Shoshone and Arapaho tribes. The cooperative movement she started was embraced by many Northern Plains Indians and still functions across many reservations of the west. Following the death of James Willard Schultz in 1947 and Jessie's retirement in 1953, she married Harry L. Graham and moved to California where she continued to work on fictional and factual writings about Native Americans of North America. Her published works appeared in Ladies Home Journal, Woman's Home Companion, Popular Mechanics, Montana the Magazine of Western History, and various educational journals. She worked extensively on a primer series about Native Americans for young school children that was never published. She continued to visit Montana and the Blackfeet [Sisika (Blackfoot), Kainah (Blood) and Peigan] of Montana and Canada during the summer months. In 1961, she was the recipient of an Honorary Doctorate of Letters from Montana State University. In the late 1960s, she donated her collection of Indian artifacts, photographs, and James Willard Schultz papers to the Museum of the Rockies. (The papers and photographs are located in Collection #10, Special Collections). In the early 1970s, the Museum of the Rockies arranged for her to tape record her autobiography. Jessica wrote a rough draft from the transcriptions of these tapes and Anne Banks (Museum volunteer) edited and created an autobiography from that material which was never published. In 1974-1975, she established the James Willard Schultz Indian Heritage Award for Indian students of Montana which was administered by the Museum of the Rockies. Jessica Donaldson Schultz Graham died on June 30, 1976.
This collection consists of originals and copies of transcriptions, a set of audio tapes; rough drafts of an autobiography; research notes; drafts of published and unpublished stories; royalty papers; legal agreements; correspondence with publishers, writers, friends and colleagues; color illustrations; pencil drawings; newspaper clippings; photographs; student papers and memorabilia. The collection has been arranged into 3 series. Series 1 contains materials related to an autobiography of Jessie Donaldson created by her and edited by Anne Banks. Included are: the audiotapes of Jessie (copied to CD) and the transcriptions with her margin notes and corrections; rough drafts by Jessie; a final draft by Jessie and Anne Banks' final edited version; an extensive set of correspondence Jessica had with Anne Banks and Leslie C. Drew, Director of the Museum of the Rockies; Anne Banks' correspondence with David Andrews (editor of the Piegan Storyteller, the newsletter of the James Willard Schultz Society), Harry James and others. Series 2 includes Jessie Donaldson's research and writings, papers, correspondence and memorabilia. It has extensive college anthropological research notes on Indians of North America from a variety of published sources, their characteristics and especially their religion with emphasis on the Blackfeet tribes [materials include a kinship list, traditional Blackfeet designs with color drawing by Paio-Taki "Flying Woman," a large collection of myth stories, Sun Dance charts and stories of her initiation into the Matokiks, The Women's Buffalo Society of the Blood Indians]; a preliminary typed plan and drafts for a series of primer books for children (with watercolor illustrations by Olga Ross Hannon); papers including play scripts or typescripts related to her production of "The Masque of the Absarokas," information and correspondence for the James Willard Schultz Indian Heritage Award, her Honorary Doctorate of Letters and congratulatory letters, her activities with the Spurs, three diaries of her activities in the 1950-1960s period and personal correspondence. Series 3 is Jessie Donaldson's papers related to the publication of James Willard Schultz stories including the posthumous books: "Blackfeet and Buffalo; Memoirs of Life among the Indian," edited by Keith C. Seele, a book derived from his stories: "Bear Chief's War Shirt," edited by Wilbur L. Betts and four books edited by Eugene Lee Silliman: three books of James Willard Schultz collected stories ("Many Strange Characters: Montana Frontier Tales," "Floating on the Missouri," "Why Gone Those Times? Blackfoot Tales") and one book of collected western stories ("We Seized Our Rifles: Recollections of the Montana Frontier"). The series includes correspondence, carbon copied and copy draft manuscripts, galley proofs, work papers and memorabilia of Eugene Lee Silliman's books; typescripts and photocopies of published and unpublished stories exchanged by Silliman and Betts; photocopied stories by Harry James about James Willard Schultz; assorted correspondence with numerous publishers including Houghton Mifflin, the Faucett Company, University of Oklahoma Press, Cavalier Magazine and others; royalties statements; publication agreements by James Willard Schultz and Jessie Donaldson including TV and film rights.
Series 1: Autobiographical material, 1969-1979
Series 2: Jessie Donaldson research materials and personal papers, 1928-1976
Series 3: James Willard Schultz's published and unpublished works, 1922-1985
Audiotapes made by Jessica Donaldson Schultz Graham are too fragile to be played, a set of CD copies are available for listening. In light of the Museum of the Rockies primary contribution in developing this collection, it is necessary that the Museum and Anne Banks be given written credit in any publication citing or incorporating the material in this collection.
The bulk of the papers of Jessica Louise Donaldson Schultz Graham and Anne Banks were donated by the Museum of the Rockies in 1985 and 2000. Integrated into the collection are collection numbers 2288 (donated by Anne Banks in 1993), 2216 (donated by Eugene Lee Silliman) and 2278 and 2387 (donated by David C. Andrews in 1972 and 1998).
Andrews, David C. (David Chisholm), 1924--Correspondence; Bear Chief (Siksika Indian)-Fiction; Drew, Leslie C-Correspondence; James, Harry Clebourne, 1896--Correspondence; Schultz, James Willard, 1859-1947; Schultz, James Willard, 1859-1947-Bear Chief's war shirt; Schultz, James Willard, 1859-1947-Blackfeet and buffalo; Schultz, James Willard, 1859-1947-Floating on the Missouri; Schultz, James Willard, 1859-1947-Many strange characters; Schultz, James Willard, 1859-1947-Why gone those times?; Silliman, Eugene Lee-We seized our rifles; Banks, Anne; Betts, Wilbur Ward; Donaldson, Jessie Louise; Hannon, Olga Ross; Schultz, James Willard, 1859-1947; Silliman, Eugene Lee
Fawcett Publications, Inc; Houghton Mifflin Company; Montana State College-Faculty; Museum of the Rockies; SPURS National Honor Society; University of Oklahoma-Press
Blackfeet Indian Reservation (Mont.); Gallatin Valley (Mont.)-Drama; Missouri River-Description and travel; Montana-Social life and customs
Boats and boating-Missouri River; Crow mythology; Frontier and pioneer life-Montana; Historical drama-Montana-Bozeman; Indian students-Montana; Indians of North America; Indians of North America-Religion; James Willard Schultz Indian Heritage Award; Kainah Indians; Piegan Indians; Siksika Indians; Siksika Indians-Fiction; Siksika Indians-Folklore; Siksika Indians-Religion; Siksika Indians-Social life and customs; Sun dance; Women college students-Montana-Bozeman-Societies, etc
Audiotapes; Diaries; Fiction; Galley proofs; Illustrations; Photographs; Plays; Short stories; Autobiographies
English teachers-Montana-Bozeman; Women authors, American-Montana-Bozeman; Women college teachers-Montana-Bozeman; Masque of the Absaroka
Colleges and Universities; Literature; Native Americans; Pioneers; Publishers and Publishing; Water and Water Rights; Women; Montana; Bozeman; Sound Recordings
- Autobiography of Jessie Donaldson Schultz Graham, edited by Anne Banks, 1969-1979; Series 1
  CD copies of audiotapes and original audiotapes; transcriptions with corrections and margin notes; a rough draft manuscript by Jessie Donaldson Schultz Graham (JDSG); an edited final version by Anne Banks and JDSG's note scraps about transcripts or manuscripts and assorted typed draft pages. Correspondence of JDSG, Anne Banks (includes correspondence with publishers exploring publishing edited version), Leslie C. Drew, other Museum staff and related mail. Audiotape CDs entries list partial subjects covered from audiotape label notes and the corresponding transcription pages. The series is organized by audio transcriptions, CD's of audio tapes, manuscripts, research notes and correspondence. (Original audiotapes are restricted) ***
  - Transcription: Tape A - E (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Transcription: Tape F - I (Box-folder 1/2)
  - Transcription: Tape J - M (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Transcription: Tape N - P (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Transcription: Tape Q - V (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Transcription: Tape W - Z (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Transcription: Tape AA - DD (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Transcription: Tape EE - HH (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Transcription: (Box-folder 1/9)
    (no tape made)
  - (Box-folder 2/1)
    (CDs)
  - Tape A: Early childhood, grandparents, Minneapolis (Box-folder 2/1)
    (pg 1-6)
  - Tape B: Childhood, dolls, sports, parties, Iowa (Box-folder 2/2)
    (pg 6-14)
  - Tape C: Missing
    (Transcribed pg 14-29)
  - Tape D: Teaching school, hunting season, dudes, Xmas celebration (Box-folder 2/3)
    (pg 29-42)
  - Tape E: After X-mas, teaching college, flu epidemic, Horse Butte (Box-folder 2/4)
    (pg 42-56)
  - Tape F: Trip to Grayling, College trips: Madison, Yellowstone, Gallatin (Box-folder 2/5)
    (pg 57-70)
  - Tape G: Spurs, Chicago and European trip (Box-folder 2/6)
    (pg 70-76+++)
  - Tape H: To Crow Agency, visits with Indians, reason for trip (Box-folder 2/7)
    (pg 77-91)
  - Tape I: New courses, production of Masque (Box-folder 2/8)
    (pg 91-98 including revised pages)
  - Tape J: No more masques, up to Blood Reservation, Matokik initiation (Box-folder 2/9)
    (pg 99-111)
  - Tape K-1: Visits to Blackfoot reservations, photos and stories (Box-folder 2/10)
    (pg 112-124)
  - Tape K-2: Back to College, 1928-1929, review of experiences, Sacred Child (Box-folder 2/11)
    (pg 124-139)
  - Tape L: Start Craft Shop, Count Folke Bernadotte, transfer to Ft. Washikie (Box-folder 2/12)
    (pg 139-152)
  - Tape M-1: Farewell to Blackfeet, reminiscences, Blood adoption (Box-folder 2/13)
    (pg 153-160)
  - Tape M-2: Arapaho mattress factory, women/shop, character of Shoshone (Box-folder 2/14)
    (pg 161-174)
  - Tape N: Petroglyth trip, Arapaho weaving, hotel drapes (Box-folder 2/15)
    (pg 175-189)
  - Tape O-1: Death of Apikuni, trip to Browning (Box-folder 2/16)
    (pg 189-204)
  - Tape O-2: Services for Apikuni, Sun Dance trips with craft workers (Box-folder 2/17)
    (pg 205-220)
  - Tape P-1: Crafts at Wind River, Teton workers, annual meetings (Box-folder 2/18)
    (pg 221-239)
  - Tape P-2: Donner Summit, Medicine Bundles, family (Box-folder 2/19)
    (pg 239-257)
  - Tape Q-1: St. Helena, primer project, work offers (Box-folder 2/20)
    (pg 257, 260, 262-275)
  - Tape Q-2: Visit historic places, Cheyenne Reservation, Indian affairs (Box-folder 2/21)
    (pg 275-293)
  - Tape R-1: Rethinking MSU resignation, Schultz's divorce settled (Box-folder 2/22)
    (pg 293-309)
  - Tape R-2: Great Falls Tribune stories, Cal.- M.A., career, 1933-1940 (Box-folder 2/23)
    (pg 310-326)
  - Tape S-T: Canada, sun lodge, discuss time-meaning, descriptions of tipis (Box-folder 2/24)
    (pg 326-343)
  - Tape U-V: Bozeman exhibit, Apikuni Memorial, Isabelle McKay (Box-folder 2/25)
    (pg 343-359)
  - Tape W: Vida's letter, Pepion visit, Illness, Albuquerque (Box-folder 2/26)
    (pg 360-378)
  - Tape X: Kutenai (Napi) myth, masque, mythology (Box-folder 2/27)
    (X1: pg 1-5; X2: pg 1-5)
  - Tape Y: Stepmothers, psychiatric readings, vision plates, missions (Box-folder 2/28)
    (pg 379-393)
  - Tape Z: Gladys' trailer, meditation-Buddhism, wood tick and dog (Box-folder 2/29)
    (pg 393-409)
  - Tape AA: Point Reyes, oysters beds, husbands' different personalities (Box-folder 2/30)
    (pg 410-425)
  - Tape BB-1: Remarriage possible, dog given away, boat trip (Box-folder 2/31)
    (pg 425-440)
  - Tape BB-2: Marriage (Harry Graham), reception, Bodega Bay (Box-folder 2/32)
    (pg 440-453)
  - Tape CC-1: Visiting friends, retired life, reminisces (Box-folder 2/33)
    (things changed) (pg 453-467)
  - Tape CC-2: Trip along 49er Trail, learning California history (Box-folder 2/34)
    (pg 467-478)
  - Tape DD-1: Mining town crime vs Montana vigilantes, Nevada visit (Box-folder 2/35)
    (pg 479-493)
  - Tape DD-2: Visiting Harry's/Jessie's families, Death Valley (Box-folder 2/36)
    (pg 493-508)
  - Tape EE: Death Valley, Lake Mead, Yosemite, nature walks and lectures (Box-folder 2/37)
    (pg 509-524)
  - Tape FF: Yosemite cont., Cloverdale, baseball, character of Montanans (Box-folder 2/38)
    (pg 524-546)
  - Tape GG: Little things, Spurs award, letters, vision interpretation (Box-folder 2/39)
    (pg 546-560)
  - Tape HH: Spurs poem, love of life, loss of husband and friends (Box-folder 2/40)
    (pg 560-581)
  - JDSG typed draft manuscript: pg. 1-100 (Box-folder 3/1)
  - JDSG typed draft manuscript: pg. 100-149 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - JDSG typed draft manuscript: pg. 150-226 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - JDSG typed draft manuscript: pg. 227-276 (Box-folder 3/4)
  - JDSG typed draft manuscript: pg. 277-350 (Box-folder 3/5)
  - JDSG typed draft manuscript: pg. 351-404 (Box-folder 3/6)
  - JDSG typed draft manuscript: pg. 405-450 (Box-folder 3/7)
  - JDSG typed draft manuscript: pg. 451-492 (Box-folder 3/8)
  - JDSG typed draft manuscript: pg. 493-549 (Box-folder 3/9)
  - Anne Banks typed draft manuscript: Introduction (Box-folder 3/10)
  - Anne Banks typed draft manuscript: pg. 1-48 (Box-folder 3/11)
  - Anne Banks typed draft manuscript: pg. 49-91 (Box-folder 3/12)
  - Anne Banks typed draft manuscript: pg. 92-137 (Box-folder 3/13)
  - Anne Banks typed draft manuscript: pg. 138-200 (Box-folder 3/14)
  - Anne Banks typed draft manuscript: pg. 201-249 (Box-folder 3/15)
  - Autobiography - JDSG prerecording notes (Box-folder 4/1)
  - Autobiography - JDSG notes from tapes for manuscript (Box-folder 4/2)
  - Autobiography - JDSG assorted draft pages for manuscript (Box-folder 4/3)
    (numbers do not match tapes)
  - Correspondence - JDSG / Leslie Drew, 1969-1976 (Box-folder 4/4)
  - Correspondence - JDSG / Anne Banks, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 4/5)
  - Correspondence - Ann Banks / David Andrews, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 4/6)
  - Correspondence - Ann Banks / Harry James, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 4/7)
  - Correspondence - Ann Banks / publishers, 1977-1978 (Box-folder 4/8)
- Jessie Donaldson research materials personal papers, 1928-1976; Series 2
  Handwritten and typed research notes and files; typed draft manuscripts; maps and lists; programs, brochures, and pamphlets; color illustrations; photographs; newspaper clippings, newsletters and magazine articles; diaries; citations, certificates and a diploma; photocopied and original personal and professional correspondence; essays and essay rules; book series materials; and assorted ephemera. The series is organized from general research materials to more specific topics, draft manuscripts and working papers, professional correspondence and then to personal correspondence and collected materials.
  - Anthropology note cards - file (Box-folder 5/1)
  - Anthropology note cards - file (cont.) (Box-folder 5/2-3)
  - Anthropology note cards - file (Box-folder 5/4)
    (loose)
  - Bibliographies (Box-folder 6/1)
  - Course notes - University of California - California Indians, 1930 (Box-folder 6/2)
  - Course notes - University of California - California Indians - drawings, 1930 (Box-folder 6/3)
    (tools, etc.)
  - Course notes - University of California - Geography, 1930 (Box-folder 6/4)
  - Course notes - University of California - Religions, 1930 (Box-folder 6/5)
  - Ethnology notes - Native Americans of North America (Box-folder 6/6)
  - Ethnology notes - Native Americans of North America (cont.) (Box-folder 6/7-8)
  - Ethnology notes - Native Americans of North America- mythologies and stories (Box-folder 6/9)
  - Ethnology notes - Native Americans of North America- mythologies and stories (cont.) (Box-folder 6/10-14)
  - Maps (Box-folder 6/15)
  - Mentor Grandmother, Sacred Child and Fire Magic myths (Box-folder 7/1)
  - Research - Fire Magic (Box-folder 7/2)
  - Research - Fire Magic (cont.) (Box-folder 7/3)
  - Research - Mentor Grandmother (Box-folder 7/4)
  - Sacred Child - He walks with the Sun - Kutenai - rough drafts and research (Box-folder 7/5)
  - Sacred Child - He walks with the Sun - typed manuscript (Box-folder 7/6)
  - Blackfeet Indian designs (Box-folder 7/7)
    [color illustrations by Paio-Taki (Flying Woman)]
  - Blackfeet Indian game (Box-folder 7/8)
  - Blackfeet kinship lists (Box-folder 7/9)
  - Blackfeet Sun Dance charts (Box-folder 7/10)
  - Wind River Reservation - booklet of collected Shoshone children's stories (Box-folder 7/11)
  - Matokik file - typed manuscripts of two versions of JDSG's initiation into the Matokik society and related papers (Box-folder 7/12)
  - Typed manuscripts of two stories by JDSG (Box-folder 7/13)
  - Typed manuscript of The Shadow Moccasin (Box-folder 7/14)
    (author unknown, possibly JDSG)
  - Typed copies of papers written by JDSG (Box-folder 7/15)
  - Let's Play Indian (children's primer) research papers (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Let's Play Indian working papers (Box-folder 8/2)
  - Preliminary outline of a primer featuring "Star Boy" and "Bird Girl" (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Indian Owl Magic primer story rough manuscripts (Box-folder 8/4)
  - Let's Play Indian Pre-Primer "The Squirrel and the Rabbit" manuscript (Box-folder 8/5)
  - Let's Play Indian proposed primer for Native Trails Readers series with color illustrations (Box-folder 8/6)
  - Let's Play Indian primer for Native Trails Readers series with color illustrations (cont.) (Box-folder 8/7)
  - Manual for Woodland Indian primer (Box-folder 8/8)
  - Notes and program for production of the "Masque of the Absaroka" (Box-folder 8/9)
  - Itemized cost lists, (1939) (Box-folder 8/10)
    Itemized cost lists for tipi painting [Count Bernadotte (1939)] and "Masque" production
  - Correspondence -publishers and others - related to primers and JDSG stories (Box-folder 8/11)
  - Correspondence with Leslie Davis - publishing of assorted collected stories (Box-folder 8/12)
  - Appointment diaries, 1956; 1963; 1968 (Box-folder 9/1)
  - General correspondence, 1928-1976 (Box-folder 9/2)
  - Gifts to Museum of the Rockies - correspondence (Box-folder 9/3)
  - Heaslip, Thomas - correspondence (Box-folder 9/4)
    (fan of James Willard Schultz from Ireland)
  - Honorary Degree: citation, program, diploma, 1961 (Box-folder 9/5)
  - Honorary Degree -congratulatory letters, 1961_ (Box-folder 9/6)
  - Indian Heritage Award - correspondence, 1974-1975 (Box-folder 9/7)
    (proposal, arrangements, rules)
  - Indian Heritage Award - essays and lists of applicants, presentations, letters from winners (Box-folder 9/8)
  - Memorabilia: typed poems, photos, brochures, pamphlets (Box-folder 9/9)
  - Museum of the Rockies: brochures, pamphlets, membership newsletters (Box-folder 9/10)
  - Newspaper clippings and newsletters (Box-folder 9/11)
  - Retirement: citation and correspondence, 1953 (Box-folder 9/12)
- James Willard Schultz's published and unpublished works, 1922-1985; Series 3
  Included materials are correspondence, royalty statements, and copies of legal agreements for published works of James Willard Schultz; photocopied articles, carbon copy and photocopied draft manuscripts, galley proofs, work papers, correspondence, newspaper clippings and memorabilia of books edited by Eugene Lee Silliman; copies of manuscripts and published articles exchanged by Silliman and Wilbur Betts; correspondence of Jessie Donaldson Schultz Graham with publishers and editors regarding posthumously published James Willard Schultz books, TV and film agreements and correspondence. The series has been filed alphabetically by subject.
  - Film and TV agreements and correspondence, 1952-1971 (Box-folder 10/1)
  - Harry James stories about James Willard Schultz, undated (Box-folder 10/2)
  - JDSG / Eugene Lee Silliman correspondence, 1971 (Box-folder 10/3)
  - Kutenai stories told to James Willard Schultz by tribal members, 1929 (Box-folder 10/4)
  - Magazine story "The Wolfers", American Boy Magazine, 1922-1923 (Box-folder 10/5)
  - Magazine story "The Wolfers" correspondence, 1960-1961; 1976 (Box-folder 10/6)
  - Publishers - correspondence - Faucett Publications Inc., 1952-1972 (Box-folder 10/7)
  - Publishers - correspondence - Houghton Mifflin Company, 1930-1970 (Box-folder 10/8)
  - Publishers - correspondence - periodicals - Cavalier and others, 1952-1969 (Box-folder 10/9)
  - Publishers - correspondence - University of Oklahoma, 1957-1967 (Box-folder 10/10)
  - Publishers - publishing agreement - Houghton Mifflin Company, 1914 (Box-folder 10/11)